good morning not sure how we're not the
w3 I don't know the rest
good morning good work I almost meditate
so first meditation step turn off your
cell phone that's a second one blow your
nose oh cloth
okay that's Cindy
and relax your forehead
and relax your lips especially the
corner of your mouth we love your
fingers pull in your stomach just a
little bit straighten your shoulders
pull your hands back just a little bit
and make your eyelids soft
and then come to your breath
and watch your breath try to count to
ten breath count number one on the
exhale and then the second exhaled is
number two and if you think of something
else before you reach tens down over
again then we'll stay here for a few
minutes
then please about your heart teacher to
come and sit in front of you could be
someone who's alive now it could be a
historical person like Buddha or Jesus
could be someone you haven't met yet
but you can imagine them
and they happily come and sit in front
of you
then gone down to God by thinking about
one of their good qualities something
you would like to learn from them
and make them an offering in gratitude
could be killing the sky with flowers
like Samantabhadra could be some
beautiful thing you've seen or heard in
the last few days
don't concuss something you've done in
the last few days that you're not very
proud of maybe said something to someone
negative one thought something then just
literally open your heart to your
teacher show them so you can clean it
then think something beautiful you've
done in the last 50 or something
beautiful you've seen somebody else to
does the hard work that the staff is
doing here all year and especially this
past few weeks is something very
beautiful you can meet your
accessibility
then ask your teacher to teach you keep
teaching when you ask it means that
you're open to learning and changing
and then ask your teacher to stay with
you without their influence you just
would continue the way you are
then the hi please start to think about
the last few days and make a list of all
the things you've done to take care of
yourself
hmm you've said to yourself you put
clothes on yourself you put yourself in
a car and got your body here you're
working to support yourself to have a
place to stay to have food and to do the
things you Mark all this intense effort
towards yourself to be happy take care
of yourself try to count the ways you
are taking care of yourself in the last
cases
now trying to get in touch with the
feeling of love that you have for
yourself it's very very strong there are
many bodies in this room human bodies
and you choose one and you comb it hair
and you buy it clothes and you make sure
it's bad you have a strong bias and this
jolly self-love is some of it salty but
compared to the love we have for others
it's overwhelming it's it's 99% of our
attention is spent trying to feel good
ourselves trying to take care of
ourselves
so don't judge it but try to become
aware of it and observe it try to
recognize it how much emotion how much
strength you put into taking care of
yourself
now think of a Buddha and they say that
Buddha loves you many thousands or
millions of times stronger than you love
yourself so the love you have for
yourself taking care of yourself making
the bed for yourself every night to
sleep in feeding yourself making sure
you look good
that overpowering love is not one
percent up the mountain a Buddha has for
you personally so try to imagine someone
who can watch you all day wherever you
are someone who can hear your thoughts
all day and knows all of your faults and
still have this love for you which is
millions of times stronger then this
dumb love you have for yourself
and bring your mind back to the teacher
sitting in front of you and realize that
they had this kind of love for you much
stronger than your love for yourself and
thank them ask them to come in your
heart and stay there and their body
starts to rise still seated in
meditation position and it comes slow me
up and gets smaller and smaller and
turns to sit in the same direction as
you and comes down on the top of your
head only as large as your summer
and then you ask that teacher to come in
to write and they shrink to the size of
a pea and then melt into the top of your
head and they come down the center
channel just and follow your spine you
can track them along your spine you can
feel them coming down slowly to your
throat to your upper chest and finally
into your heart then they start to get
smaller and smaller almost as if they're
staying inside of a crystal globe tiny
until they reach the size of a grain of
sugar inside your heart and it's easier
to picture them and keep them there if
you picture them very small it helps
your mind focus
and they're smiling and they're happy
and they love you and they will stay in
your heart out they protect you
guide you love you
and compact your breath three count
three long exhale don't open your eyes
yeah don't move three long exits on the
exhale sending that good karma seeds out
to all the people in this world that
they have a good day to earth day
then you can open your eyes stretch take
us get drink something
okay we should keep water
okay welcome to l'm rim LOM remain steps
of the past and this is the 25th
retreatment
yeah yeah we're trying to finish a
famous lemon teaching by Bob Alcorn PJ
who was the teacher of my teacher and my
teachers teacher yeah
and so he's your great-great-grandfather
something like that it and my teacher
taught this book to me for I don't know
25 years three times true and I think
it's the greatest book in this world so
it's cool to have friends together and
learn it together one more time and and
I think it will save your life okay
I think it will save your life if you
come if you can't come I know it's
expensive and it takes a lot of time to
get here so if you can't come listen to
it on the knowledge base okay I think
all of them are daring I don't know and
many of them are in Chinese and other
languages and we're trying to translate
them Scott oh the guy who runs the
knowledge base is getting it up soon
yeah he works really really hard and he
doesn't ask for money he takes money but
he doesn't ask for me
but I try to keep up with it try to
follow it even if you can't come I think
it will be the best thing you did in
your life
and especially when you get older and
something worked wrong with the sound no
sound on the Chinese got it
I think the Chinese has no son Germany
son as you get older you'll understand
that this is the most important thing
you do are you is to get ready for
higher things and it's very frustrating
for me I got this was a bad month last
month I got I think 15 emails from
people who someone was dying in their
family or where they got some terrible
disease I got an email from a woman that
I haven't heard from for 20 years
I know email for 20 years then I got an
email I have cancer my mother died what
can I do you know and I'm it's so
frustrating for me you know I I said
please come to the first 25 retreats 24
then they want me to help them in in 10
minutes or 20 minutes you know it's not
possible I can't you know they want me
to see some prayer in their their
mother's soul will go to heaven or
something and it's too late you know you
can't listen to the knowledgebase after
you die easily
so I think it's just really important
that you're here and that you keep going
and I know you've heard some of these
things before
some people complain to me you didn't
say anything new today and I'm like well
maybe the old stuff is good you know or
maybe we need to hear it again you know
so some people have been coming to these
classes for I don't know 25 years and
I'm sorry if I don't say anything new I
had me stuff when you're ready but you
know I'm just following the text a lot
of you came here through DCI teachings
around the world and that's going really
really well I'd like to thank all the
Chinese organizers and we had a two-week
tour with a few weeks ago and 7000
people came to the teachings and that's
amazing and people in China Taiwan
worked so hard to make the teachings
available for people and I'm really
grateful for that and I thank you for
that and it's going like that around the
world so people are working really hard
and a lot of the people here are
teachers or organizers in different
countries and it's you know it's your
job right to make it available to people
my teacher said he got upset because we
weren't advertising his teachings very
well we actually didn't advertise them
at all because we like to be a small
group
and he got angry one day I seem to get
angry and he said how come all these
other teachers people advertise all this
stuff and you don't advertise my stuff
and you know and we're like you're too
good to need advertising humor it's kind
of weird to advertise Dharma then he
said no I understand it's not good to
push Dharma body said if you don't let
people know it's available you did a
very bad thing you know you have to let
people know it's available who want to
come you know I went to a yoga class in
Phoenix and this guy I had taught for
four days in Phoenix and then I went to
a yoga class and me and this guy ran up
to me so I guess he Michael I said I
wish you would come to Phoenix and teach
as I just finished four days of teaching
but he didn't hear about it you see so
we have to let people know it's there
you know we shouldn't push them or you
know squeeze them but we should let them
know it's there right
okay so mmm I'm going to review a little
bit from what we did in Thailand last
time and I thought I would go through I
I put the first three meditations in
your meditation book are from Thailand
are from the teaching in Thailand and I
would like to thank Jasmine right now
she worked really really really hard
she made it possible for 400 people to
come to that retreat and she just been
unbelievable amount of energy and time
to make it available for people and
thank you for that
she said she's gone for 600 this year I
know but there's a beach there we have
fan but no beach you know if you're not
busy in December you can come she said
she found a really nice hotel a little
bit more expensive but my Samantha okay
on the beach so anyway I'm going to
review three of the meditations we did
in Phuket in Thailand just to catch up
people who weren't there so you know
where we are okay so the first
meditation what would it be like to love
more than myself have you do remember
that one we did it about five minutes
ago
okay that's a trick question okay we did
that one around five okay so that was
the first meditation that's part of the
long rim where we've reached a part
where we talked about protection and how
to get protection you can call it
protection you can call it shelter you
can call it refuge
but how do you get protection when you
have problems or in your life so a big
part of that protection is to recognize
that there is a person who loves you
millions of times stronger than you love
yourself they are ready to protect you
and I just want you to come and ask okay
so that was the first meditation there
is a being many Buddhist they know what
you're thinking they watch you all day
they're probably wincing all day but
they care about us and and you have to
understand that they're there they are
waiting and they like to protect you
they want to help you okay you just have
to learn how to reach them okay so that
was the first meditation and that's the
first review from what we did in
Thailand the second one which is
meditation number two here and I like to
use photographs for the meditations
because I can remember photographs
easier so for example if you're a
teacher and you're teaching like come
unless you learn something memorize the
photographs memorize the flows of
photographs and and then you can teach
it without notes a friend of mine paid
for me to take a voice lesson with a
jazz famous jazz musician
last week and he's like now the first
thing you gotta know man if you can't
you can't just look at the paper and
sing a song that just don't work it's
not kind of work and so you do away my
note you know and teaching is the same I
think you know generally unless you're
following a text word by word it's you
can memorize the slow of the photograph
and when you're in between which is
starting day after tomorrow yeah it's
good if you can memorize the the
meditations that you have to do then if
you forget you can peek okay but just
remember the photograph okay first
photograph is run somebody admiring them
stuff in the mirror okay
that's self-love okay she's in love with
herself okay
but Buddha's love for you is much much
stronger okay got it
are you one can we turn on the air and
freeze the people in front did you bring
your coat Jenny okay who's gonna turn on
the air
Nick can you turn on the air-condition
okay second meditation what is the
highest form of power and then you have
a guy pointing the way for hiking you
know they're going on a hike and the
guys pointing the way so you can
remember the photograph and then it says
the limits to the unlimited so this is a
famous expression in this long rim where
they say the unlimited has limits okay
the unlimited here means Buddha okay
Lord Buddha and the idea is that even
Lord Buddha has limits okay and what do
you think they are
yeah good but I can't help you unless
you have the seeds for it okay like
that's a difference between Buddhism and
Christianity for example in Christianity
we believe that God made you and God can
do anything God can change you into a
turtle today can do anything but in
Buddhism we believe Buddha has limits
Buddha can't help you if you don't have
the seeds you can and Buddha cannot take
bad seeds out of you Buddha cannot put
good seeds into you Buddha can only
teach okay Buddha can only teach so of
all the things Buddha does speaking is
the most important okay Buddha can only
tell you how to plant good seeds then
you have to do it yourself okay so that
means he's he or she is limited okay
they have a limit to what they can do
for you okay
and they can only teach you so when we
talk about taking refuge going for
protection its limited how much
protection you can get you see unless
you plan to seek for the protection okay
ultimately the love that Buddha has for
you was created by you okay by your seat
okay and the protection is created by
you okay so when you do the second
meditation which we'll do together it's
thinking about what I have to do to get
protection okay I have to do something
from my side to get protection okay
probably it has to do with helping other
people have protection okay like if you
ignore people whose country is being
demolished tell them they can't come
here then you can't expect protection
for yourself okay things like that okay
third meditation and by the way it's my
goal to go through all these I think
it's twenty seven meditations in the
next two days even before we reach them
in the text okay and in some of them we
will reach in the text after your
retreat after your meeting between but I
want you to meditate on them while
you're near India three days yeah there
are 27 meditations basically okay ok
third meditation if I could answer like
a mirror then when you stand in front of
a mirror
[Music]
you don't have to ask the mirror to show
you yourself it's just automatic that's
the nature of a mirror when you put
something in front of a mirror the
mirror will show it automatically you
don't have to ask the mirror please show
me myself okay you just stand in front
of the mirror and they thought of
matting okay and the idea here is that
the way of buddha serves people is
automatic it's like a mirror okay when
you provide the mirror buddha will be
there okay when you give buddha a place
to come buddha will come and buddha
doesn't think about it it's called some
good robust and goopy and it's such an
important idea that many monks are
called syndrom guesses simples first
named master slender in Wisconsin so it
means subject means it just shows up
automatically a hundred means
automatically okay when you reach
enlightenment you have the power to show
up automatically when someone needs you
so a person in need is like a mirror and
a Buddha will show up there and there's
a beautiful section in the long room
we'll get to it's like the moon reflects
in any body of water and it doesn't
matter if it's a Pacific ocean or a lake
or a puddle on the street in Hong Kong
or a tear in someone's eye if there's
water surface the moon will shine the
moon will appear in that water doesn't
matter where it is or how big it is or
how small it is Buddha will appear
Buddha will come
if you have okay alright okay if you ask
them they will come okay
and that's Thunder they don't think
about it it just happens okay it's
automatic when someone needs them they
show up okay so when you do the third
meditation goodness without thought I
would like you to will meditate it will
practice it together but I like you to
think about what it would be like to
have that power
okay what if I had that power you know
so I like to think I don't know why I
always see a bus in Guangzhou and a old
lady in Los Angeles and maybe somebody
in Paris and they're all having a bad
day in three different cities around
this world and then Buddha appears to
them you know and I think it's very
common that Buddha will appear as a
small dog for old ladies that's why so
many old ladies have small dogs because
Buddha just appears they need company
their husband died and they feel lonely
and then Buddha will appear as a small
dog and they can walk the dog and you
know like that they will appear on a bus
to help an old lady off the bus into the
bus or something like that you know huh
they are doing this stuff
now all the times every moment dad doing
this all over the world they're just
showing up when people need them okay so
I think it'd be nice when we do that
meditation you think about how it would
be to have this power okay you want to
do it right now let's turn right no yes
so get ready to meditate I want to do
each meditation with you at least once
before you do your retreat sit up
straight
turn off your phone I notice the cell
phone towers are getting closer we might
have to move yeah put on something to
keep yourself warm Jenny you have cook
okay good let's go
sit up straight pulling your tummy just
a little bit bring your shoulder blades
together open your chest relax your
fingers
come to your breath try to learn to come
to your breath quickly bring your mind
down into your breath quickly
then try to imagine yourself as you will
be a Buddha and you will see that Buddha
directly for the first time when you see
emptiness directly right after that
experience in in a few hours following
that experience you will see yourself as
you will be a Buddha taking care of an
entire world so I'd like to look at this
Buddha as standing on top of the sky you
know so their feet are on of their feet
are facing the verse but they are
standing high above the atmosphere
standing on the atmosphere venerable
jing-mei asked me what shall we call a
press that we have for printing Buddhist
books I said let's call it standing on
the sky press so you're standing and you
are looking down at your world that
you're in charge of it's your
responsibility as a Buddhist to focus on
this particular world
and help the beings in this world so you
feel sort of like a mom watching her
child in a crib or something this is
your world to help take care of it and
I'd like you to imagine this Buddha is
like a moon shining full moon and then
down there on the surface of this earth
our bodies of water oceans lakes puddles
teardrops
and you're like of your moon shines in
each one as soon as the water faces you
you appear in the water like a mirror
like stepping in front of a mirror that
does bodies of water or people who need
something so I'd like you to imagine the
Americas the South in North America and
choose a city that you comes to mind and
imagine someone in that city who needs
help today and you decide what kind of
help it could be they just lost a
boyfriend or girlfriend or husband or
wife or they just found out that they're
very sick to have serious disease they
just lost their job they don't know what
to do you choose a city and you choose a
an imaginary person or someone you know
in the Americas who has a problem
and then imagine that you step in front
of that mirror and you become someone or
something that can help them maybe is a
dear friend or a child who comforts them
or a teacher or a little dog you choose
something and step in front of a mirror
the person who needs you and imagine
you're helping them in a place in the
Americas
and stay in that body of the friend or
the dog in the Americas and then move
your mind to Europe look down on Europe
Western or Eastern Europe and to the
city
and then decide think of a person who
might meet you let's do the whole strip
like Middle East Africa Europe
and think of someone who needs something
to the city create a imaginary person or
think of a person you know about say in
Syria or something and come to their
miss and a friend protector someone to
love reflect in that mirror in that
puddle of water of a person who needs
you but don't let go that the one in
America in the Americas keep that one
going and create a circle
now move your mind to Asia North concern
and do the same thing think of any city
to the city
ho Chi Minh Singapore Jakarta Hong Kong
Shanghai Beijing you choose
imagine a person there who has some
problem don't let go of the first two
bodies you took in the Americas and in
this trip of your husband Middle East
Africa hold those two now choose a city
in Asia
imagine someone in troubles needs help
or to someone you know and step in front
of that mirror of a person in need and
appeared suddenly in their life as a
friend or a teacher or maybe as their
child someone they can love
and enter the third body at the same
time as you keep the other tooth
and keep the straight bodies going
shopping three different kpop and bring
your mind back to yourself standing on
the sky those three bodies are still
living helping people but bring your
attention back to yourself that's a good
standing in the sky
and then three long access to combat
and then slow the other guys take a good
sketch
[Music]
we caught up to Thailand so I think it's
a good time to take a break okay so we
took us 10 minute break so my idea for
this teaching this book was to go
through the original tibetan word my
words because i would like to have a
record of it in the world before i take
any trips so so i I would like to you
know I know maybe if you don't know
Tibetan it seems strange or it's boring
but I don't care because I want to
finish it in my lifetime I want to have
a record of it so I will go through the
Tibetan word by word and when there are
special words that would be helpful to
know for our translators we have a
translator team they are working on I
think 23 books they have a project of 23
books it's scheduled to go to 2024 and
sorry I will pause sometimes and explain
a word that I think they might need ok
so if you don't like that approach just
come to DC I okay but this is the backup
for DC I okay this is the foundation
this is where DTI comes from so I think
it's good to hear it okay the filter
process is that 1000 people come to a
talk at the Union Trade Center in
Singapore then 100 people will come to
the Swiss club for a retreat
and ten of dogs will come to Diamond
Mountain you see so you are one out of
you know sorry one will come to impose a
way so you're at the bottom of the
filter you know you are the people who
are most serious and you're going to
hear the original scripture and you will
during this week and especially in
Guadalajara you will say oh that's where
this guy comes from or that's where that
comes from
okay all right and I think it's
important to do both I think it's
important to reach normal people with
normal language and I think it's
important to have the backup of the
ancient scriptures and you should have
both okay
and then we have to translate it into
Spanish with a bigger team that we had
in Taiwan we had level 8 and the manual
is four hundred and something pages 450
pages and the Chinese translation team
organized by Stanley
[Applause]
[Music]
guess how many people work on the
translation 81 81 81 translator and they
finished in one week okay so it's an
example for Spanish okay we have to talk
about it we need to get going okay all
right here we go
uh who's we get a projector - my god
Simon Chan young GUI I don't know
jeez eh eh n Y ang you got it Shinyoung
something going on up there oh okay
it's secret all right Shan young couch
or 210 extension duo so these are other
examples of Buddha doing things total is
an unusual word here it means miracles
so Buddha will show miracles like Jesus
turned water into wine and walk on water
and in Buddha often does the same thing
symptoms do walk - to impress students
and get them to do things you know okay
generally it's not a preferred method
because it doesn't last then next week
people say I want a bigger miracle you
know so it's better if people just can
understand the scripture and follow it
but sometimes it's good to show a
miracle for people and it changes their
life okay so we can they choose symbols
then the main quality of Buddha's speech
is to teach them of course okay
and your mum everything is a lot then
they took you 10 aw so then the Buddha
is in a constant state of perfect
meditation
okay so they act from a state of deep
meditation on time and then they they
can do things out of that meditation
like emanate as the wind and teach us
you know I like to try to listen to
trees when they rustle and see if
Buddha's talking to me you know like do
that it's like that okay Doris I get on
memorable Rock madam
so up to the eighth bodhisattva mammals
Petzl rock bar means obvious effort they
have to make an obvious effort to do an
action it's with decision and with with
a lot of decisions and thinking about it
they will help somebody
okay up to the eighth Bodhi softly level
we are when we help people we have to
think about it and then we have to make
plans and then we have to work hard to
make the plans come true like funding
diamond mountain or some things and it
takes a lot of effort and conscious
thought okay up to the 80s after level
now you can guess what he's going to
sing next
yeah after that okay day Yankee chunks m
ki young cool on tomalak douching date
oh nice and gentle Taylor do GB Tim name
in June then 8th 9th 10th Bodhisattva
levels the Bodhisattva is subtle it's a
subtle cooling Tamil means subtle
motivation they they have a very subtle
thought to help somebody and then it
happens they can make things happen
without a lot of planning and without a
lot of intention it just kind of happens
they say well I'd be nice at die
mountain high enough
then next week it has enough money okay
like that okay so eight nine ten
Bodhisattva bevels it's still a subtle
intention to help people is required to
take actions okay now what you're going
to say yeah but we need to get a Buddha
it's like stepping in front of a mirror
okay it's automatic
you help people automatically okay Sam
Chen Tom Taylor due to pitching them
into means even eighth ninth tenth
Bodhisattvas with they're very subtle
intentions it's the Chinese have no
problem the Chinese it's okay
something wrong with the Chinese
it's okay if you need batteries through
your memory okay how does Alma there's a
better one good charge Stanley good huh
okay oh okay
so because they still have to think
about it a little bit a bodhisattva
after eighth ninth and tenth levels
cannot help all beings at the same time
not possible because you know there's
too many people
all right son Genki team they need but a
buddhist activity same Genki don't
y'all gone by a good long jump into so
cloud meter part they don't think they
never think I should go help this person
or this other person needs help or you
know I should I should get down there to
Los Angeles right now and help that
person they don't think that they don't
have time right part paramdham get down
run Mina for example similar to the moon
in the sky number topham a without any
kind of conscious thoughts
Shin do SATs a silver soon done cheered
on to new boom top mobile so the word
here is Shilpa or SIL was simple this
comes in the diamond cutter Sutra in the
last few lives karma Robert my main
argument super chill Bhutan you must
super to Bordeaux famous poem
like a star like an illusion which one
is here yeah like a drop of dew what's
he going to say yeah the moon will
reflect even in the morning when there's
a drop of dew on the grass then the moon
coming down right will show in that job
okay
at 9:00 okay do on the tip of a blade of
grass even there the moon will appear
okay
sundown to nibble talk mumble and in
billions of open pots of water glasses
of water around the whole world
number two Moony this was useful to know
n gos not a Muslim and it means the
surface of something so the surface of a
wall is calmer the surface of the water
is come and the word to recognize
someone is called holding their surface
Munson okay look learning punishing is
clear crystal clear this is a beautiful
Tibetan word if you want to learn it Don
Hossler
lhasa tongue okay and it means
crystalline clear it's a very beautiful
word and it's also the word for faith
it's one of the words for faith so it
can refer to clear Mountain Springs or
it can refer to how a person feels about
their teacher or something like that
okay Tom okay
dunking my you know if the water is not
moving okay
what's that means yeah if the mind is
clear the Buddha can reflect there if
the mind is not quiet
if the water is shaking it won't show
the reflection of the moon okay
signe and charlatan then that reflection
took me in' will appear in that water
till JQ todd me here's the important
part this sentence is very important
okay let's do it
do Jake you taught me to lead Killa
Bubba Bubba no do Jake you talk with dog
pure he's my human dictionary
okay dog name means on insta I got a
charley horse I apologize if the if the
disciples heart is pure okay
doc no doc 'no that's very important
qualifier okay if the disciples heart is
pure tag me do a doula pavana and if
it's time to tame them okay doula is
what's the sanskrit denial okay if it's
time to vinaya size them okay meaning if
they're like acting wrong but if their
heart is pure okay do i do LaBeouf now
if it comes time to correct them
sangeeta new dimension to the joopa you
here's the words under then they may
often come from syndrome it means
effortless effortlessly automatically
the buddha will appear to help them okay
that that's a buddhist quality alright
if it's time and if you have the seeds
then dussangha cute in a shape around
you yes you chew kudaki and chipper so
basically what we call the holy activity
of a Buddha which is called Tinley okay
that's also a popular name there's a
tenday attendant to me in the video
guinea mini if you remember he was my
first teacher his reincarnation
tenzin 10 days so 10 day means that the
activities of a Buddha okay
holy activities shape around you you
sheets you could darken chepa darken
means what's the what's the cause inside
a person that creates these bodies
showing up in Buenos Aires and Berlin
and Hong Kong okay what's the cause
inside a person okay
it's yes you cuckoo okay yes you too
cool we learned we were debating it here
I forget last time we were here we were
debating how many Buddhists
how many bodies does a Buddha have okay
and tell me what's the right answer two
or three or four and um say since five
[Music]
huh all the above
who said that you can't answer all the
questions yeah you can divide Buddhist
body which just means the parts of a
Buddha in this case body means parts
okay there's two parts or three parts or
four parts okay two parts means physical
and mental okay
Rupa kaya dharmakaya physical body and
I'm a bunny okay three parts you can
split the you can split the physical
body into two the one that they keep in
heaven the one that they send two places
and then their mental body when you're
divided into four there's the physical
body in their paradise there's a
physical body they sent to earth there's
their mental body their wisdom their
state of mind and then there's the
emptiness of these three is called their
reality body okay emptiness body
okay so essence body low in eco
swappable kaya so
this what he's talking about is this
third one the mind of a Buddha okay yes
you too ku that triggers the emanations
without intention okay if you have a
Buddhist mind you will show up in every
city in the world where someone needs
you and you you don't have a choice and
you don't think about it it just happens
the trigger is your state of mind okay
that's what he's saying the trigger
darken means to trigger inside of a
person okay the inside of person trigger
is his wisdom okay and if you have that
state of mind even if you don't want to
you will show up in many cities to help
people okay
like the moon reflecting in water okay
he finished talking about the cool how
cool a Buddha is and he's going through
the three jewels because this section is
about taking refuge right to the three
jewels which is by the way what makes
you a Buddhist okay so in Christianity
you get baptized okay then you become a
Christian in Judaism something goes to
it anyway fit right anyway I went I went
to one of these ceremonies I couldn't I
couldn't stay but in Buddhism when you
take refuge then you're a Buddhist okay
when you take refuge in the three jewels
okay so there's two interesting
possibilities one is if people
understand the pent very well they take
refuge by accidents and they all become
Buddhist even if they don't want to and
then then there's lots of Buddhist
people who are born in Buddhist families
who want to be a Buddhist but they don't
know about the pen so they're not a
Buddhist okay
all right NEPA chicky and Danny what are
the cool things about the Donna refuge
okay Fujimoto birch a pagina
now i think this is one of the most
important parts in this book okay
did I say that 300 times already ah but
it is okay
what's a Dharma what is Dharma okay and
what's Dharma Refuge okay and here he
talks about the real one and the one
that's not real okay and and he he oh we
call he shows his cards you know he
shows you what's real what's true here
right here okay you want to be a
Buddhist this sentence okay ready
simcha Motti TIPA TIPA yenna if people
have had a chance to get a good Buddhist
education if they came to many lamrim
retreats okay if they went to many DCI
levels okay if he says if tol impart a
melon double then you can explain to
them that the direct perception and
emptiness is the ultimate taking refuge
period emptiness is refuge if you
understand the pen you are taking refuge
if you understand the pen your Buddhist
if you don't understand the pen frankly
you're not a Buddhist
okay got it okay here's where he says it
so if I say that in a DCI program you
know where it came from
okay total imparting Mellon which means
the direct perception emptiness during
the papacy Double Dragon will Kalki drip
upon consumption if you're just aware of
how understanding emptiness can help you
to remove your negative thoughts forever
then your bliss okay if you're aware
of how emptiness can help you be a
better person then you're a Buddhist
okay now I'm going to give a real-life
example because it's in your meditation
book okay
let's look at number meditation number
is that guy
meditation number 15 and 16 I repeated
it I repeated a picture in both
meditations what's the picture the two
husband's okay this is what we call a
DCI life tool there are 96 DCI life
tools okay once you know them you're
really smart okay this is one of them is
called the two husbands
all right does the lady look happy
no why the husband is yelling at her
what does it mean a we could do it up
here no no no we should good huh well
mix really good and shoutings good at it
you come come quick be the husband I'm
the wife
you're one of the husbands okay
these are my three bad kids right here
okay I'm the wife you know I'm a working
woman okay so I have three naughty kids
she's almost real life and and then I
have a husband okay
then I'm working full-time because the
husband likes to watch soccer and he's
not interested in so anyway my life is
like that five days a week I take my
kids to school before I go to work and
then I work for eight or ten hours if I
live in Guangzhou I probably work for 14
hours and then I come home but on the
way home I have to buy groceries because
my husband's watching soccer not penny
of course but uh so then when I come
home I'm really really tired okay
exhausting so you know the story because
that's your real life now on on Tuesday
afternoon my boss tells me that on
Wednesday morning I have to come in
early probably because we have a Skype
call with the Vasek in America and we
live in China so I don't know why they
can't have a Skype call in the middle of
the night it's always the Chinese who
have to have the Skype call in the night
and my boss told me don't forget you
have to come I want you here at 8
o'clock in the morning not 9 o'clock
okay so then Tuesday 9:00 I have to tell
my three kids you know tomorrow Mommy
has to go to work early and you know so
I want you to be dressed for school not
at
not a seven o'clock but like 6:30 okay
and have your homework finished and be
dressed and have your shoes on and
everything and then mommy's got to take
you to school earlier because Mommy has
to burn okay then they promise see how
they're nodding and then next morning
when mommy walked in the room dad
jumping on the bed you don't have to be
dad jumping on the bed
they don't have their school clothes
bombed they lost their shoes nobody can
find them they're under the bed
someplace then the mommies like I told
you to be ready and then I am so stupid
you want to stop with this kissing
poncho you know like that okay then
mommy who heard mommy yeah the three
kids
maybe they heard me they didn't but
mommy here's mommy okay
when mommy here's mommy say bad thing
mommy makes a bad seed that plants a bad
seed in mommy's mind okay next week
Monday bad day right Monday's always the
worst day so you go to word you had a
long day you took the kids to school you
went to work your boss kept you late
I'll tell your interesting thing about
bosses they give you so much trouble if
you show up late in the morning but they
don't they're not shy to ask you to stay
late in the afternoon well why is that
my boss he starts screaming at me you
know you're late you're ten minutes late
I said you kept me three hours late
yesterday I'm ten minutes late you kept
me to Mijares late you know they think
they don't understand you know so it
keeps me late then I come home sorry I
went to buy groceries because my
husband's watching a football game
soccer thing then I'm tired you know
then I come home and all I want the
reason I have a husband the only reason
because he doesn't work much is to give
me hugs you know I like to have some
that feeling of him hugging me you know
that's why I keep him you know and then
I'm looking forward to having a hug you
ready come home legs open the door I'm
home phone and just then the husband
call you Rice bucketheads because you're
late right the husband is upset because
husband getting get dinner during the
soccer game okay then they call you
stupid
all right now normal the normal reaction
is what no move on don't know meet Nisan
dong you're a phantom you know I'm not
I'm not right bucket head
you're right okay like that okay that's
normal reaction okay
what happens if you do that who here did
you hear it plants another seat next
week he will do again okay because he's
coming from you okay he's like a pin
he's coming from you okay why did he
yell are you yeah because you planted a
seed last week last Wednesday you
planted seed okay he's coming from you
whose fault yeah it's your fault okay
now bad news every irritating person you
ever met
what's coming from you everyone most
people want to say geshe-la 90% of
people I mean who are irritating coming
from me but my ex-husband he's not
coming from me
he's so bad
okay make things up things that it's
really a hundred percent okay it's
really a hundred percent so if you
so this husband called shopping okay I I
believe not coming from me not my fault
you can take a deep breath and you could
say in one word I didn't do anything I
didn't do anything I just opened the
door I didn't do anything and then he
called me phantom I own I don't know
what it is okay that bad husband not my
fault that husband not my fault does it
exist or not doesn't exist okay that
husband we call in buddhism in tibetan
we call it who said gotcha nice okay
that's a self existent thing that's
that's a gotcha that's the thing that's
not there and that's the meaning of
illusion okay it looks like he's there
but it's not there that's Maya that's
illusion okay don't don't get all
mystical on me
okay it's not mystical it's all about
husbands okay that that husband is Maya
that husband appears to be real and
doesn't exist the husband who's not I
didn't do anything
so my fault that husband doesn't exist
never existed will never exist cannot
exist okay because it's not coming from
you that's impossible
that's the impossible husband now the
other husband Nick the lousy husband
right now
that one is my fault that one I created
last week with my three bad kids okay I
planted a seed by hearing my own thing
right and a planet seed next week the
seat opens picture comes out goes on top
of Nick's body and mine okay that's
dependent origination if you want to use
stupid long Buddhist words okay
Syd came out see it open up dependent
origination let's just call come from my
seeds same thing okay he comes from me
okay does that husband exist yeah he's
dependent origination okay she's
emptiness okay they go together
okay she doesn't exist that one isn't
there
that's emptiness okay the the absence of
this husband in the universe it's called
emptiness okay the presence of this
husband who comes from my seeds is
called dependent origination every time
you meet anybody until you are eighth
level Bodhisattva there will be two of
them in the room there will always be
two of them in the room okay there's
always two husbands in your room in your
kitchen always okay always because your
mind is still making this false fake
ones but you know that it's not true
there's two husbands in the room all the
time now big big big big big big big big
question when you get upset and you want
to say now I'm not stupid you're stupid
okay when you're so stupid you're stupid
by planting a new city okay
I said now yes given okay when you get
upset when you get angry which husband
are you angry at chopping or Nick yeah
shall be Alison okay so learn something
understand something
every time you got upset or nervous or
frightened or worried in your whole life
you are worried or angry or frightened
about something that wasn't there and
all war in this world world world war
two killed a hundred million people
thirty five million in China okay from
Japan right they killed a hundred
million people those enemies didn't
exist okay hundred million people died
being hating someone who wasn't there
but it killed 100 million people and
said I mean it's amazing it's it's
incredible
okay got it now what happened what do we
call it if you say oh you I understand
where you come from it's because I yell
at my kids last week you know I won't do
that again okay what's that called when
you use emptiness to stop your anger
what's that called nirvana is called
nirvana
that's the definition under burner okay
I will not get angry because I know I
will plant another sin then you stop the
cycle that's called
you broke the wheel of life okay you
brought some time okay cool okay two
husbands can sit down okay good thank
you for being good husbands
[Applause]
if you want to call somebody fun tone if
you want to say no you're stupid you can
go in the toilet the bathroom look in
the mirror thing yo stupid okay alright
Tony I'm parking my laptop Rani Mukerji
dip upon to soak something thinking
about how you're going to get rid of
your anger by not getting angry at a
husband who's not come from you is
called taking lessons got it
that's refuge that's protection you just
protected yourself in the future okay
that's all okay forget all this numbers
and ion number what I are normal and I'm
are Sam Bowden shadow number you know
forget all that use it in your kitchen
don't use it in the dump truck okay
temple is already peaceful okay kitchen
is none okay you get there take refuge
there when you have a problem take
courage
that's real Buddhism and all those
people in many countries studying DCI if
they if they follow this yeah I think
I'm going and it's okay they don't know
because they don't have to be British I
don't care just be happy reaching your
mother okay okay
give up on Chuseok some if you think
about how you can get rid of your anger
by understanding that the people who
upset you or the traffic jams that upset
you are coming from what you did last
week then you're to Christmas and that's
all got it cool we could just go home
now or we can have a five-day party
okay dad are misshape a but we have 15
13 more minutes okay so hang in there if
you think your body's tired now wait
till five days her mouth okay they
taught me Amy
NAR Sanjay mikela endemic membership is
indeed iconic tuna google also top
autonomy to attend a junction chumina
gyllideb equivalent in youngest son
Domitian - endemically in them then he's
kind of talking about people who are not
intelligent enough to understand the two
husbands
okay people who are not intelligent
enough to understand the two husbands
everybody in this room if you got here
in the middle of nowhere you probably
have enough dharma IQ dharma
intelligence to understand the two
husband's easily but then millions of
people can't understand it
you know you explained it very carefully
and then they go home and yelling it
nothing happens they don't change
okay those people you can teach them
okay just say namo buddhaya number die
Maya makes them insane you know you know
he said okay that's okay
those people who can't understand this
one the two husbands don't teach them to
go to Temple teach them to make incense
you know teach them some small mantra or
money pay me home you know it's okay
that's alright because they're not ready
for the real refuge okay
reshaping me by the way people can be
very intelligent and not have dhamma
intelligence it's different right there
are many very intelligent people who
hurt other people and think it's okay
okay so it's not the same right as
normal intelligence functional worldly
intelligence okay
all right dead a machete Myanmar
sentiment opinions and our membership is
indeed a common tumor so you can explain
to the person about all the cool things
of the Buddha okay go glance October the
moon get you locked in a changing gym
Rana but really you have to split Dharma
into two kinds somebody tell me what
they are
yeah the books and the ideas okay the
books and the ideas you know in this
book Dharma yeah it's done okay and it
will it can protect you it's okay
but the idea that the understanding the
two husbands that's real protection okay
whether you use it or not I don't know
but it can protect you if you use it
okay but you have to use it okay so
taupe here it says stupid on ligature
you have to use both really write this
expression taupe I'm long is so popular
in Buddhism that some monks name is loom
talk you know okay ten a junction Jelena
cello dedicating and then younger son so
that brings us to this meditation number
four can you show the photo yeah
when you get to when you're in your
three-day retreat you'll be doing a
meditation on this picture okay
and it's supposed to show both kinds of
Dharma jewel okay this is both kinds of
Dharma jewel what's the first one the
book what's the second one
it's the idea behind that smile okay
there's an idea like six inches behind
that smile in here okay and that's the
real Dharma jewel okay so this is
picture is supposed to show the two
kinds of damage wrong okay and when you
do that meditation you can think about
the two kinds of Dharma jewel okay
like all how many Dharma jewels do I
have in my life I have longed men I have
common less human have desire level one
level two number three okay you can
count the physical damage jewels you
have okay and then you have to count the
mental ones you have mainly three Lum so
numb so the three principal paths the
word path and Buddhism means idea it
doesn't mean the road okay three pencil
what are three pencil that first one
yeah I just see life is troubled life is
trouble okay if you don't do anything
you will get old and something this life
or good life is a problem you should
feel sad about it okay if you think
things are going well just wait a while
so she going to have to go to doctors
everyday you know like the body falls
apart okay I was reading of Princeton
magazine about ah they're trying to cure
old age but what they figured out was
they can't cure old age by carrying
separate diseases like you can't cure
diabetes and then cure cancer and then
cure heart attacks it doesn't matter
because what they found out is a person
who gets a person who died from diabetes
is going to die in three months from
heart attack anyway you see if you cure
the diabetes they would die from heart
attack in a few months if you occur the
heart attack they will die from cancer a
few months after that because the body
all falls apart at the same time that's
why they got diabetes you see I mean you
have to change the cells or you have to
change the Karma okay but the first
principle path is just be aware how
messed up things are okay just be aware
it's not things I'm not going well in
this realm okay people are killing each
other people who are getting old and
they're going to die anyway are killing
other people are going to get old and
dying anyway
why why spend the time you know how to
do something else for a while because
you're both going to die and you're
thinking why bother kill somebody
okay this that's the world it's messed
up
okay the world's messed up right now
okay we're this realm there's other
realms that are not messed up we're just
in a bad neighborhood
okay all right
second principle power yeah bodhichitta
I would like to do something to help
everybody
okay very basic I would like to change
myself to help everybody else okay third
one
yeah understand it understand the pen
that's all those three ideas are
Buddhism those the ideas are damaged or
the real Dharma job okay
the world's messed up I would like to do
something to help in and understanding
the two husband's is how we can get
there okay no more fighting okay I about
Diamond Mountain all over the world
I say diamond is one place where people
will say somebody calls them stupid they
go like this no you're like that's the
sign of real practice at Diamond
Mountain you know I call it half
finished sentences you know that's a
sign that Dharma is going on at Diamond
Mountain there are more half any
sentences here than any place else I
ever saw people are like milli okay four
more minutes I'm going to use every
minute okay we were studying how to
teach teachers and we found a guy the
most popular teacher Princeton said when
he said oh three principles of great
teaching number one know your material
number two get to know your students
number three let class out early but
it's not going to happen okay
cheer cheer coin joke me generally
speaking Dharma jewel gold pendant on
gone party melon table was such a number
so much inkyung generally the Dharma
jewel is when you can no longer get
angry which we call the truth of
secession okay when you reach a point
where you can't get mad anymore because
you understand where things are coming
from that's called that's the third
noble truth third our interest okay Tull
um seeing emptiness directly golem
getting rid of your negativities party
mail um
the direct portion of the prophecy satu
ten bodhisattva thomas l'm not the five
pass etc that's the real damage or those
realizations okay but come but dear you
do what so teachers and jetsam radical
arsenal M&D taboo children when once you
die in some but when you're teaching
people who can't get it then fall back
to dharma you know fall back to books
and and counting lists and you know
trying to get them you throw the heart
sutra at them throw the diamond cutter
to tear them make them look memorize
heart sutra anything teach them a mantra
you know if they can't get it you know
then okay give them the physical diamond
give them the physical timer okay that's
what he says here if they can't get it
you'll do it so teacher the point is to
help people so singe eight some Rafa
Rafa means coal our coal elements give
me something any fool can understand
okay Cola Rock but give them approximate
Buddhism okay Shanna give him la Marie
he said it not me
okay got it
you learned I'm enjoying this yarn you
don't need all this Lamia but it's good
to know right okay so I'm we should i
and then he said when Shiva Tommy's I
told you that already
he mentioned it before okay all right so
real Dharma jewel understanding the two
husbands understanding the pin okay
you're lucky because I didn't teach you
the Pentagon
maybe not okay